<?xml version="1.0"?>
<chapter xml:id="news" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0CR7/xsd/docbook.xsd"
>
  <title>What's new in Pustefix 0.17.x</title>    
  
  <para>This section lists the new features and enhancements of the current Pustefix release line. 
        If you're interested in new features which already became available with the prior Pustefix release line,
        you can take a look at <xref linkend="newsarchive"/>.</para>

  <section xml:id="news.0_17_0">
    <title>What's new in Pustefix 0.17.0</title>
  
    <para>Pustefix 0.17.0 focuses on XSLT rendering improvements. It brings the so-called render extensions, a mechanism which allows
          to call an extension function to produce additional output and write it to the result of the main transformation (on the last
          transformation level).
    </para>
    <para>The default render extension implementation, the so-called render include mechanism, supports the standalone rendering/outputting of 
        include parts.
        Thus you're able to include parts at runtime, e.g. based on the data from the result tree. In contrast to the traditional runtime
        includes, which are restricted to simple content and a subset of tags available on the last transformation level, the render includes support     
        arbitrary content because the metatags and master XSLT transformations are also applied (see <xref linkend="xslt.renderextensions"/>).
    </para>
    <para>
        Render include parts not just can be rendered within a regular main transformation, but can be also rendered standalone, i.e. you can 
        request a rendered part via AJAX to dynamically update your page. 
    </para>

    <para>If you're migrating an existing appliation to Pustefix 0.17.0, you should have a look at <xref linkend="upgrade"/>.</para>
  
  </section>

</chapter>
