<?xml version="1.0"?>
<chapter xml:id="news" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0CR7/xsd/docbook.xsd"
>
  <title>What's new in Pustefix 0.19.x</title>    
  
  <para>This section lists the new features and enhancements of the current Pustefix release line. 
        If you're interested in new features which already became available with the prior Pustefix release line,
        you can take a look at <xref linkend="newsarchive"/>.</para>

  <para>If you're migrating an existing appliation to the new Pustefix version, you should have a look at <xref linkend="upgrade"/>.</para>

  <section xml:id="news.0_19_0">
    <title>What's new in Pustefix 0.19.0</title>
  
    <para>Pustefix 0.19.0 focuses on upgrading the underlying technologies/libraries. It added support for Servlet API 3 and Spring 4.
          The legacy dependency to Apache ORO was removed, i.e. stuff like regular expressions and LRU caches now are implemented completely
          based on the JDK standard library.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="news.0_19_4">
    <title>What's new in Pustefix 0.19.4</title>
  
    <para>Beginning with this version the Pustefix 0.19 line becomes the main development line. All new features from 0.18 now are available
          in 0.19 too and the development of the 0.18 line will be discontinued. It's recommended to upgrade existing applications to 0.19 soon
          (see <xref linkend="upgrade.0_18_to_0_19"/>).
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="news.0_19_8">
    <title>What's new in Pustefix 0.19.8</title>
  
    <para>Passing through the last pageflow using the <literal>__lf</literal> URL parameter has become optional. It can be disabled using the new configuration switch
          <literal>&lt;disable-pageflow-passthrough/&gt;</literal> (see <link linkend="configuration.servlet.contextxml.passthrough">configuration section</link>).
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="news.0_19_9">
    <title>What's new in Pustefix 0.19.9</title>
  
    <para>Pustefix now supports modularized log4j configurations and provides an appropriate default configuration, which helps keeping the logging configuration
          up-to-date with the latest Pustefix version and simplifies the maintenance of complex application logging configurations 
          (see <link linkend="configuration.logging.includes">logging configuration</link>). Additionally Pustefix now allows changing of log levels at runtime
          via JMX.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="news.0_19_11">
    <title>What's new in Pustefix 0.19.11</title>
  
    <para>Extended form error checking tag by optionally supporting IWrapper parameter prefix/name and request trigger conditions, and adding a new tag
          with inverted semantics (see <link linkend="xslt.forms.errors.fields">tag reference</link>).
    </para>
    <para>Improved render include Javascript library: support for passing arguments as JSON object, HTTP error callback functions
          (see <link linkend="xslt.renderextensions.javascript">Javascript example</link>).
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="news.0_19_14">
    <title>What's new in Pustefix 0.19.14</title>
  
    <para>Added new Maven plugin for generating a complete list with display names of all renderable pages, e.g. can be used for automatic testing.
          (see <xref linkend="tooling.mavenplugins.pagelist"/>).
    </para>
    <para>Beautified and more SEO-friendly URLs by removing the <literal>__reuse</literal> parameter from redirect URLs (replaced by Spring flash attributes).</para>
    <para>Pustefix now provides a simple Spring/annotation-based event mechanism. It should replace the deprecated way of coupling <literal>ContextResources</literal>
          using the <literal>ContextResourceObserver</literal> and <literal>ObservableContextResource</literal> interfaces (see <xref linkend="advanced.eventbus"/>).</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="news.0_19_15">
    <title>What's new in Pustefix 0.19.15</title>
    <para>Added support for rendering pages with non-200 status code (see <literal>SPDocument.setResponseStatus()</literal>) and 
          overriding declared error pages (see <literal>SPDocument.setResponseErrorPageOverride()</literal>).
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="news.0_19_17">
    <title>What's new in Pustefix 0.19.17</title>
    <para>Added support for Spring profiles. Pustefix now by default activates a profile for the current execution environment mode
          (see <xref linkend="configuration.spring.profiles"/>).
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="news.0_19_21">
    <title>What's new in Pustefix 0.19.21</title>
    <para>Added support for using Google Closure Compiler to compress inline Javascript (default compressor will be the YUI compressor, if available in the classpath).
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="news.0_19_23">
    <title>What's new in Pustefix 0.19.23</title>
    <para>Improved rendering perforamnce (by extension function caching).</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="news.0_19_24">
    <title>What's new in Pustefix 0.19.24</title>
    <para>Added new <literal>DefaultIWrapperState</literal> method <literal>handleWrapperErrors</literal> for processing validation errors,
          e.g. to log them.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="news.0_19_25">
    <title>What's new in Pustefix 0.19.25</title>
    <para>Added new <literal>Context</literal> method <literal>invalidateSessionAfterCompletion</literal> for guaranteed invalidation of 
          session after current request has been processed.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="news.0_19_27">
    <title>What's new in Pustefix 0.19.27</title>
    <para>Added new tool for analyzing XSL transformation performance.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="news.0_19_28">
    <title>What's new in Pustefix 0.19.28</title>
    <para>Improved rendering performance for pages with lots of runtime includes (by include extension function caching).</para>
    <para>Added servlet filter for performance logging.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="news.0_19_29">
    <title>What's new in Pustefix 0.19.29</title>
    <para>Improved rendering performance for pages with lots of internal links (by caching callbacks).</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="news.0_19_30">
    <title>What's new in Pustefix 0.19.30</title>
    <para><emphasis>We officially discontinue support for Java 1.7!</emphasis> This is the first version which makes use of Java 1.8 features. 
          Almost a year after the EOL of Java 1.7 it's really about time to say goodbye.</para>
    <para>Added support for generating request IDs which let you correlate log entries with specific web requests (see <xref linkend="advanced.requestid"/>).</para>
    <para>Added Eclipse m2e lifecycle mappings for Pustefix plugins to improve Eclipse IDE integration of Pustefix projects.</para>
  </section>

</chapter>
