<?xml version="1.0"?>
<chapter xml:id="upgrade" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0CR7/xsd/docbook.xsd"
>
  <title>Upgrading to a newer Pustefix version</title>

  <section xml:id="upgrade.0_16_to_0_17">
    <title>Upgrading from Pustefix 0.16 to 0.17</title>
    <para>
      Pustefix 0.17 should be fully backwards compatible with 0.16. But the new render include mechanism required massive refactoring of
      the core XSL templates to make them independent of the page parameter on the master and metatags transformation levels. So you should
      invest some time into QA and especially check if buttons and links work as expected.
    </para>
  </section>
    
  <section xml:id="upgrade.0_15_to_0_16">
    <title>Upgrading from Pustefix 0.15 to 0.16</title>
  
    <section xml:id="upgrade.0_15_to_0_16.web_xml">
      <title>web.xml</title>
      <para>
        With Pustefix 0.16 URLs referencing pages no longer contain the <literal>/xml/xyz</literal> path prefix. Thus the according servlet
        mappings in <literal>src/main/webapp/WEB-INF/web.xml</literal> became obsolete. You can remove all <literal>&lt;servlet-mapping/&gt;</literal>
        elements containing an <literal>&lt;url-pattern&gt;</literal> starting with <literal>/xml</literal>.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="upgrade.0_15_to_0_16.project_xml">
      <title>project.xml</title>
      <para>
        In Pustefix 0.16 URL paths no longer start with <literal>/xml/xyz</literal>. You should adapt the according path configurations
        in <literal>src/main/webapp/WEB-INF/project.xml</literal>.
        Within the <literal>&lt;application/&gt;</literal> section you can remove the according path configurations:
        the <literal>&lt;default-path&gt;</literal> element and 
        the <literal>&lt;path/&gt;</literal> elements beneath <literal>&lt;context-xml-service/&gt;</literal>,
        <literal>&lt;direct-output-service/&gt;</literal> and <literal>&lt;deref-service/&gt;</literal> (if available).
      </para>
      <para>
        The <literal>&lt;additional-trail-info&gt;</literal> element now is optional. If missing, Pustefix by default registers
        the default <literal>AdditionalTrailInfo</literal> implementation <literal>org.pustefixframework.http.DefaultAdditionalTrailInfoImpl</literal>.
        You have to be aware that the package name of the interface and the implementation changed from <literal>de.schlund.pfixxml.perflogging</literal>
        to <literal>org.pustefixframework.http</literal>. You either will have to adapt the package names, or if you're relying on
        the default implementation, you can just remove the complete <literal>&lt;additional-trail-info/&gt;</literal> element.
      </para>
      <para>
        The elements <literal>&lt;perflogging&gt;</literal> and <literal>&lt;testrecording&gt;</literal> became obsolete because the 
        performance logging and testrecording mechanisms are no longer 
        part of the Pustefix core framework. You can just remove these elements. The <literal>&lt;authadmin&gt;</literal> element is also no 
        longer supported and should be removed.
      </para>
      <para>
        If you're referencing a XML schema, you can change the schema location to
        <literal>http://www.pustefix-framework.org/2008/namespace/project-config-0_16.xsd</literal> to get an updated version.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="upgrade.0_15_to_0_16.depend_xml">
      <title>depend.xml</title>
      <para>
        With Pustefix 0.16 URLs of all kind of pages (dynamic, directoutput) are directly served under the servlet context without using an additional
        path prefix. Therefore every page requires a unique name. If you use the same page name multiple times, e.g. for normal and directoutput pages,
        you will have to rename it making it unique.
      </para>
      <para>
        No longer requiring a path prefix for pages, you can remove all <literal>handler</literal> attributes from the
        <literal>&lt;page/&gt;</literal> elements within the <literal>&lt;navigation/&gt;</literal> section.
      </para>
      <para>
        If you're referencing a XML schema, you can change the schema location to
        <literal>http://www.pustefix-framework.org/2008/namespace/xml-generator-config-0_16.xsd</literal>
        to get an updated version.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="upgrade.0_15_to_0_16.taglib">
      <title>Tag library</title>
      <para>
        The <literal>&lt;pfx:image/&gt;</literal> tag behaviour changed when used within XML includes coming from modules. Without specifying
        a module using the <literal>module</literal> attribute, the image source now is searched within the module itself instead of the
        webapp. You either have to add the <literal>search="dynamic"</literal> attribute to look up the image in the webapp before trying to
        get it from the module or you can set the <literal>module</literal> attribute to the special value <literal>WEBAPP</literal> to force
        getting it from the webapp.  
      </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="upgrade.0_15_to_0_16.modules">
      <title>Modules</title>
      <para>
        Pustefix 0.16 no longer extracts resources from modules (the former <literal>resource-mappings</literal> from the Pustefix module
        descriptor are ignored now). Pustefix itself meanwhile can load every type of required resource directly from the module Jar files.
        If your application code directly accesses extracted resources, e.g. using <literal>java.io.File</literal>, you will have to change
        this and switch over to loading the resources via the classpath, ServletContext or Pustefix's resource abstraction layer.
      </para> 
    </section>

    <section xml:id="upgrade.0_15_to_0_16.sessions">
      <title>Session handling</title>
      <para>
        Since 0.16 Pustefix supports different session tracking strategies, whereas the new cookie based approach became the default strategy.
        Although Pustefix tries to make session id handling transparent to the application by hiding it in its core templates and internal code,
        there are use cases where applications directly access the session id, e.g. for creating links without using the core tags.
      </para>
      <para>
      	Because URL rewriting of the session id now by default is only done if the client disabled cookies, you will have to adapt code, which
        manually creates session-aware links. You should only include the session id, if necessary. Therefore Pustefix introduced two new 
        XSL parameters: <literal>__sessionId</literal>, which is always set to the current session id, and <literal>__sessionIdPath</literal>, which
        is set to the path extension for the session on demand , e.g. <literal>;jsessionid=xyz</literal>. The <literal>__sessionIdPath</literal> parameter
        will be empty if the session id came from a cookie. Thus you can easily create session-aware URLs by just adding the value to your URL
        without having to take care if cookies are enabled or not.
      </para>
      <para>
        The XSL parameter <literal>__sessid</literal> was removed as its contract doesn't exactly match one of the new parameters. You will have to
        replace it according to your requirements using one the new ones.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="upgrade.0_15_to_0_16.webservices">
      <title>AJAX webservices</title>
      <para>
        The JSON and SOAP Javascript libraries were moved from the Pustefix core module to the Pustefix webservice modules.
        If your application uses these libraries, you will have to adapt the according <literal>script</literal> tags, replacing
        <literal>pustefix-core</literal> by <literal>pustefix-webservices-jaxws</literal> or <literal>pustefix-webservices-jsonws</literal>,
        e.g.
<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<script type="text/javascript" src="{$__contextpath}/modules/pustefix-core/script/webservice.js"></script>
<script type="text/javascript" src="{$__contextpath}/modules/pustefix-core/script/webservice_json.js"></script>]]></programlisting>
        has to be changed to:
<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<script type="text/javascript" src="{$__contextpath}/modules/pustefix-webservices-jaxws/script/webservice.js"></script>
<script type="text/javascript" src="{$__contextpath}/modules/pustefix-webservices-jsonws/script/webservice_json.js"></script>]]></programlisting>
      </para>
      <para>
        Generated Javascript SOAP stubs aren't delivered statically any longer, i.e. you also have to use the <literal>pfx:wsscript</literal> tag
        to include the stub file (instead of statically referencing it), e.g.
<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<script type="text/javascript" src="{$__contextpath}/xml/wsscript/MyService.js"></script>]]></programlisting>
        has to be changed to:
<programlisting language="xml"><![CDATA[<pfx:wsscript name="MyService" type="soap"/>]]></programlisting>
        The <literal>type</literal> attribute only is required if you enabled multiple webservice protocols for the service within the configuration.
      </para>
      <para>
        If you manually build webservice URLs, e.g. if you don't want to use the generated stubs, you have to be aware that the request path no
        longer contains the <literal>xml</literal> part, e.g. you will have to change <literal>http://anyhost/xml/webservice/MyService</literal> to
        <literal>http://anyhost/webservice/MyService</literal>.
      </para>
    </section>
  
  </section>
  
</chapter>
