<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Projects and user data</title>
  </properties>

  <body>

  <section name="Projects and user data">

  <table>
    <tr valign="top">
      <td>
        <p>The <i>Projects and Administration</i> page of the Pustefix editor.</p>
        <img src="../images/editor_prodsel.png"/>
      </td>
      <td>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <td><b>Box No. 1</b>lists all available projects and allows you to select one of them for editing. 
              After selecting a project the editor starts on the <a
              href="tools.html">Tools</a> page and you will see
              a toolbar where you can select what kind of project
              browsing or editing you want to perform.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><b>Box No. 2</b> provides buttons to show all editor sessions and locks and a button that allows you
              to change the data of the user currently logged in. For more information about this see below.</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td><b>Box No. 3 is only available for admin users</b>.
              Pressing the <i>Prohibit new logins</i> button will prohibit all new login attempts.
              The <i>Useradmin</i> button allows the administrator to create, delete and change other users of the system.
              See the screenshots below for more information on this.
            </td>
          </tr>
        </table>
      </td>
    </tr>
  </table>

  <subsection name="Managing users">
  <p>This screen allows an administrator user to create, edit and delete users.</p>
  
  <table>
    <tr valign="top">
      <td>
        <p>The <i>Useradmin</i> page.</p>
        <img src="../images/editor_useradmin.png"/>
      </td>
      <td>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <td>
              To create a new user enter the new userid in the <i>Add new user</i> section 
              and press the <i>Create new user</i>button.
              Afterwards the <i>user data</i> page appears (see below).
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              To edit a user press the <i>Edit</i> button in the user list. Afterwards the <i>user data</i> page 
              appears (see below) already filled with the current user data.
            </td>
          </tr>
        </table>
      </td>
    </tr>
  </table>
  
  <p>This page is for editing user specific data like name, section, phone
    and password. Additionally you can define the rights a user has to edit
    different parts of your project(s). This is explained below. </p>
  <table>
    <tr valign="top">
      <td>
        <p>The <i>user data</i> page when editing the standard <i>CMS User</i>.</p>
        <img src="../images/editor_useredit.png"/>
      </td>
      <td>
        <table>
          <tr>
            <td><b>Common rights</b>: These rights are shared among all existing projects.
              There are two common rights. The first determines if the user has admin role.
              Admins are allowed to edit anything and can manage all user data. The second
              determines if the user is allowed to edit the default branch of dynamic
              includes like statuscodes. The default branch of dynamic includes is used
              by all projects which do not have a product specific branch of them.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <b>Project specific rights</b>: As the name says a project specific right 
              is only valid for a single project. It consists of a set of three
              special rights. Every project has such a set of rights.<br/>
              The first determines if a user is allowed to create and edit 
              include parts for the project. With this right you are also
              allowed to create and delete product specific branches.
              If you want to modify an include 
              which is used by another project you must have the '<i>Edit Includes</i>'
              right for this project.<br/>
              
              The next one determines if a user is allowed to upload images
              for the project. If you want to change an image which is used
              by another product you must have the '<i>Edit Images</i>' right for this
              product.<br/>

              The last right determines if you are allowed to create or edit product
              specific branches of dynamic includes.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              Note: The words 'project' and 'product' are used synonymical here.
            </td>
          </tr>
        </table>
      </td>
    </tr>
  </table>  


  </subsection>
  </section>
</body>
</document>
