<?xml version="1.0"?>
<chapter xml:id="architecture" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0CR7/xsd/docbook.xsd"
>
  <title>Architecture</title>
    
    <section xml:id="architecture.high-level">
      <title>High Level View</title>
      <para>
        <xref linkend="architecture.high-level.figure"/> shows the two main parts of the Pustefix system.
        On the left you can see the java framework. A request coming from the browser enters the business
        logic. After the processing has finished, the business logic delivers the result as a (in memory)
        DOM tree. To get a more detailed overview of the business logic, take a look at
        <xref linkend="concepts"/>.
      </para>
      <para>
        The stylesheet that's responsible to render the UI to displays the result data is requested from
        the XML/XSLT generator. It uses the DOM tree as input to create the HTML output that is displayed
        on the browser.
      </para>
      <figure xml:id="architecture.high-level.figure">
        <title>High Level View of the system</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/reference/architecture-high-level.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
        The stylesheet generator makes heavy use of caching to ensure that transformations are never made
        twice unless the result is out of date. Normally all generated stylesheets are cached in memory
        (and on disc). If you don't have enough memory to hold your site in RAM, you can specify other
        cache objects. E.g. we supply a LRU cache that can be configured to hold only the last N generated
        objects in memory.
      </para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="architecture.backend">
      <title>The Pustefix backend system</title>
      <para>
        <xref linkend="architecture.backend.figure"/> shows, how the different interfaces and classes
        in Pustefix are connected.
      </para>
      <figure xml:id="architecture.backend.figure">
        <title>The Pustefix backend system</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/reference/architecture-backend.gif" format="GIF"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
        <para>
          Please note that this graph is somehow out-dated as <literal>de.schlund.pfixcore.workflow.Context</literal>
          is no longer a class but only a interface providing the application's view on the functions provided by the
          "real" context implementation used by the servlet.
        </para>
      </figure>
    </section>
    
    <section xml:id="architecture.xsl">
      <title>Recursive XSL Transformations</title>
      <para>
        The XML/XSLT System of Pustefix is responsible for generating the final stylesheet that
        represents the static content of a page. This stylesheet is then used together with the DOM
        tree that holds the result of the request (as given by the business logic) to produce the
        final HTML output.
      </para>
      <para>
        <xref linkend="architecture.xsl.figure"/> shows the typical transformations and files that are
        involved in producing the final stylesheet <filename>BazPage.xsl</filename>.
      </para>
      <para>
        Note that we only discuss the common case here, arbitrary complex and deep transformation trees
        are in fact possible.
      </para>
      <figure xml:id="architecture.xsl.figure">
        <title>Recursive XSL transformations</title>
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/reference/architecture-xsl-transformations.png" format="PNG"/>
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>
      <para>
        The red boxes are supplied by the framework, you don't need to create them yourself and as an
        application programmer, you can't change them. Currently this is only the case for
        <filename>core/xsl/master.xsl</filename>, <filename>core/xsl/metatags.xsl</filename>,
        <filename>core/xsl/customizemaster.xsl</filename> and other stylesheets that make up the core
        environment (these are not shown as they are included into <filename>master.xsl</filename> and
        <filename>metatags.xsl</filename> via <literal>xsl:include</literal> transparently for the user).
      </para>
      <para>
        The green boxes are the result of XSL transformations.
      </para>
      <para>
        The blue boxes represent files that you need to create yourself. The <literal>[PROJECT]</literal>/xsl/skin.xsl and
        <literal>[PROJECT]</literal>/xsl/metatags.xsl files are special, as they are not a target (see below) but just another
        XSLT stylesheet that can be included via xsl:include into master.xsl and metatags.xsl resp.
        <literal>[PROJECT]</literal>/xsl/skin.xsl contains the project specific templates that should apply on the last
        transformation stage, while <literal>[PROJECT]</literal>/xsl/metatags.xsl contains the project specific templates that
        apply only on the first stage.
      </para>
      <para>
        There are projects that don't use a <literal>[PROJECT]</literal>/xsl/skin.xsl stylesheet at all or include even more
        stylesheets. Making master.xsl aware of the presence of the <literal>[PROJECT]</literal>/xsl/skin.xsl stylesheet is
        part of the transformation from core/xsl/master.xsl + core/xsl/customizemaster.xsl --> master.xsl
      </para>
      <para>
        It'a also posible that a project doesn't use a <literal>[PROJECT]</literal>/xsl/metatags.xsl stylesheet or includes
        more stylesheets: Similar to master.xsl it's the responsibility of the transformation from
        core/xsl/metatags.xsl + core/xsl/customizemaster.xsl --> metatags.xsl to customize the resulting 
        metatags.xsl to include the stylesheets.
      </para>
      <para>
        The <literal>[PROJECT]</literal>/xml/FooBase.xml file defines the structure of the "BazPage" page (e.g. frames, the outer
        table structure if you do the layout with tables or divs and the like). You define one of these
        structural xml files for every layout you want to use in your project (the number of structural xml
        files is typically quite small, as many pages share the same layout).
      </para>
      <para>
        The blue discs blue discs represent include parts. These are little snippets of XML code that make 
        up the actual content of the page. As can be seen from the diagram, they can include each other, as
        long as there is no cyclic inclusion (so no include part can include itself either directly or
        indirectly). Include parts have a name and are organized into so called include documents. These
        can hold an arbitrary number of parts.
      </para>
      <section xml:id="architecture.xsl.targets">
        <title>XSL Targets</title>
        <para>
          A target is everything that is the result of a XSLT transformation as seen in <xref linkend="architecture.xsl.figure"/>.
          It is also obvious that a target can be used to create new targets. For the sake of completeness,
          the initial XML or XSL files that are used in transformations are called targets, too.
        </para>
        <para>
          The Pustefix system knows different types of targets:
        </para>
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Leaf targets are targets that are not the result of a XSL transformation, but are read
              directly from files. You only edit leaf targets, never virtual targets.
              The distinction between XML/XSL is made depending on the purpose the target serves.
              An XML target is read into the system without doing any special processing, while an XSL
              target is compiled into a templates object that is able to transform XML input.
            </para>
            <para>
              Examples for leaf targets in <xref linkend="architecture.xsl.figure"/> are <filename>FooBase.xml</filename>,
              <filename>core/xsl/metatags.xsl</filename> and <filename>core/xsl/master.xsl</filename>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
          <listitem>
            <para>
              Virtual targets are the result of a XSL transformation. They don't exist as files
              (in fact they do, but only to cache the result on the harddisk. These cache files must never
              be edited by hand). The difference between the XML/XSL type is the same as with the leaf targets.
            </para>
            <para>
              Examples for leaf targets in <xref linkend="architecture.xsl.figure"/> are <filename>BazPage.xml</filename>,
              and <filename>BazPage.xsl</filename>.
            </para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </section>
    </section>

</chapter>