<div>
  <h1>The servlets used in <pustefix/></h1>

  <p>
    The processing of a request in <pustefix/> starts with a servlet
    that is derived from <code>de.schlund.pfixxml.ServletManager</code>.
    This class implements session creation, redirecting into sessions,
    handling of SSL and other services for it's descendants.
  </p>
  <p>
    The main feature of it's session handling is that it's mostly
    transparent to the user. You can submit data to a URL, and the
    system will take care to store the supplied data, create a session,
    redirect to the URL with an embedded session id, and continue with
    the business logic and the data submitted with the original
    request afterwards.
  </p>
  <p>
    Even SSL is handled transparently. A descending servlet must
    implement the method <code>+needsSession(): boolean</code> to
    decide if the the current request should result into the session
    to be "secure". You don't have to make sure that the webpages use
    "https://" in all needed links, the target itself tells the system
    that it want's to run under SSL.
  </p>
  <p>
    If the servlet decides that from now on it want's to run under SSL,
    a complex redirect sequence happens that makes sure
    that all data is copied from the previous insecure session into
    a new, secure session (a session is secure if it's session id was
    never transmitted over an insecure channel). After a session has
    once transformed into a secure one, there's no way back: Every
    time you try to use the session with "http://" it will create a
    new, secure session dropping the old one (because it's tainted now).
    If the visitor's browser supports cookies, the system manages
    to map request with the old, original, insecure session id (which
    can happen whenever the user uses the back button of her browser
    to go back to a page that has still the old session id embedded in
    every link) to the new, currently running secure session and
    silenty and securely redirects to this session.
  </p>
  
  <stdimg src="img/java_servlets.png">
    The commonly used servlets
  </stdimg>
</div>