<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Changes</title>
  </properties>
  <body>
    <release version="0.7.0" date="in cvs">
      <action dev="jenstl" type="update">
        More relative paths for configuration files.
      </action>
      <action dev="mlhartme" type="remove">
        Removed <code>common/conf/projects.prj</code>, the necessary data 
        is read from <code>servletconf/projects.xml.in</code> now. 
      </action>
      <action dev="mlhartme" type="remove">
        Removed the following properties from depend.xml: record_dir, cachedir and docroot. 
        Pustefix automatically passes them to the xslt processor, you don't have to
        mention them in depend files.
      </action>
      <action dev="mlhartme" type="update">
        XML dependencies are concentrated in three files (in the <code>de.schlund.pfixxml.util</code> package):
        <code>Xml.java</code> for parsing and serialization, <code>XPath</code> for xpath compuations, and 
        <code>Xslt</code> for XSL processing. 
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.7" date="2004-08-06">
      <action dev="jenstl" type="remove">
        The tomcat distribution has been removed from the skeleton, the install instructions
        describe how to get it.
      </action>
      <action dev="jenstl" type="fix">
        Various Tomcat 5 fixes.
      </action>
      <action dev="mlhartme" type="add">
        Enable stylechecker and fix missing copyright headers reported by it.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.6" date="2004-08-03">
      <action dev="mlhartme" type="update">
        Switched from Tomcat 4.1.30 to 5.0.27.
      </action>
      <action dev="mlhartme" type="update">
        Convert documentation to xdoc and configure a maven build. 
        The <code>docs</code> directory is gone, all documentation resides in 
        <code>xdocs</code> now.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="0.6.5" date="2004-07-11">
      <action dev="ecker" type="update">
        <p>Replaced the Java applet based editing area with one based completely 
        on JavaScript. Now we finally have a solid foundation to build upon. The 
        new editing area has not many additional features for the time being, but 
        this will change. For now,</p>
        <ul>
          <li>The syntax highlighting should just work.</li>
          <li>You can indent a line or a selected region by pressing TAB.</li>
          <li>For reasonably sized include parts, it's much faster.</li>
        </ul>
      </action>
      <action dev="rrapude" type="add">
        <p>Added <code>pfixcore-examples.tar.gz</code> with three very basic example 
        applications which can be unpacked into the the projects directory of the 
        environment.</p>
      </action>
      <action dev="jenstl" type="update">
        Cleanup and bug fixes on our way to xslt 2.0. We already have another branch 
        where this work is done now, called SAXON_8. Please see there if you're 
        interested in this.
      </action>
    </release>
    <release version="0.5.4" date="2004-06-01">
      <action dev="jenstl" type="remove">
        Removed <code>needsData()</code> as part of the
        <code>ContextResource</code> interface. This was never really
        needed anyway.
      </action>
      <action dev="jenstl" type="update">
        Internal cleanup (please refer to the ChangeLog or
        the documentation on this site for more details). But note that
        <i>you need to update your depend.xml.in files</i> when using this release!
      </action>
      <action dev="jenstl" type="add">
        Implemented a very simple form of "aliasing" for pagerequests in the config files.
        Many different pagerequests can now share their configuration details.
      </action>
      <action dev="jenstl" type="add">
        Added the possibility to jump into a pageflow without directly
        specifing the target page. The page that will be used is
        determined to be the first page needing data from the given pageflow.
      </action>
      <action dev="jenstl" type="add">
        Added the possiblity to add <code>FlowStepAction</code>s to
        every step of a pageflow. These actions consist of a list of
        XPath expressions acting as tests on the generated result DOM
        which will trigger an associated action (like "jump to another
        page") when they match. These tests are run whenever the
        relevant flowstep want's to continue with the pageflow. Using
        this mechanism it's possible to change the whole pageflow run
        depending on the state of the application (if this state is
        reflected in the result DOM).
      </action>
      <action dev="jenstl" type="add">
        Added a new configurable exception handling. The current system will
        be changed to use this system shortly.
      </action>
      <action dev="jenstl" type="add">
        Simplified and normalised the depend.xml.in file syntax even
        more. Now also metatags.xsl is a customized version of core
        stylesheet (much like master.xsl)
      </action>
      <action dev="jenstl" type="add">
        Moved to XSLT 1.1 for the core stylesheets. This will help with
        the time it still takes for the transition to XSLT 2.0.
      </action>
      <action dev="jenstl" type="update">
        Changed the way parameters and commands are associated to a
        special submit button. They are no longer completely encoded
        into the name of the button, instead only a prefix is
        transmitted as the name while the parameters are put into
        special named hidden input tags.
      </action>
      <action dev="jenstl" type="fix">
        <b>...and many many bugfixes</b>
      </action>
    </release>

    <release version="0.5.3" date="2004-03-23">
      <action dev="jenstl" type="add">
        You can now set a pageflow even if the current page is no
        member of that pageflow. This allows to enter into any
        pageflow after the submit to the current page returns
        successfully.
      </action>
      <action dev="jenstl" type="add">
        The request parameters <code>__jumptopage</code> and
        <code>__jumptopageflow</code> are similar to the common
        <code>__page</code> and <code>__pageflow</code> parameters,
        but they specify a page (and the associated pageflow) the
        system should jump to unconditionally after a successful
        submit. In other words: If there is a
        <code>__jumptopage</code> set, the system won't start the
        usual pageflow process, but instead jump to the specified page
        (selecting, if it exists, the value of <code>__jumptopageflow</code> as the
        new pageflow)
      </action>
      <action dev="jenstl" type="update">
        We upgraded our embedded tomcat to version 4.1.30
      </action>
    </release>
  </body>
</document>
