<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<document>

  <properties>
    <title>Where to get it?</title>
  </properties>

  <body>

  <section name="Where to get it?">

  <p>
    Pustefix can be <a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=72089">downloaded</a> 
    from SourceForge. Alternatively, you can checkout from <a href="cvs-usage.html">CVS</a>. 
    The files to download are shown in the table below.
  </p>

  <table>
    <tr>
      <th>
        Filename
      </th>
      <th>
        Content
      </th>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>
        pfixcore-skel-&lt;VERSION>.tar.gz
      </td>
      <td>
        <p>
          Contains an pustefix environment with all you need develop pustefix application.
          Download this if you are new to pustefix.</p>
      </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>
        pfixcore-&lt;VERSION>.jar and pfixcore-data-&lt;VERSION>.tar.gz
      </td>
      <td>
        <p>Contains the pustefix core with all java classes and the necessary XML/XSLT files.
        Usually, you will download an pustefix environment which includes the core.
        Download these files if you already have an pustefix environment and want to 
        upgrade it to the latest core.</p>  
      </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>
        pfixcode-examples-&lt;VERSION>.tar.gz
      </td>
      <td>
        Example projects. 
      </td>
    </tr>
  </table>

  <subsection name="Prerequisites">

  <p>
    There are a few things you need to have installed prior to using Pustefix. See the 
    table below for references. <i>Note that we changed our skeleton distribution to no longer include Tomcat,
    you now have to dowload it from <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/tomcat/index.html">jakarta.apache.org</a>.</i>
  </p>
  
  <table>
    <tr>
      <th>
        Package/Library
      </th>
      <th>
        Notes
      </th>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>A unixoid OS.</td>
      <td>Yes, java should be platform independent.
          Unfortunately portions of the build environment and code
          are unix specific. Although these platform independant
          portions mainly deal with file system path secifications -
          they exist. There may be even more places where the thing
          wouldn't work on win32.</td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="http://java.sun.com/j2se/">J2SE &gt;= 1.4.1</a>
      </td>
      <td>
        The Java 2 Platform, Standard Edition (aka Java Development Kit)
        in version 1.4.1 or higher.
      </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="http://jakarta.apache.org/tomcat/index.html">tomcat</a> 5.0.x
      </td>
      <td>
        The tomcat servlet container. You need to get this together
        with the skeleton package to have a complete pustefix
        environment. We currently develop against
        tomcat-5.0.27. Please note that you need to download the
        binary package in the form of a gzipped tar file
        (.tar.gz). Don't unpack it, just put the downloaded package in
        the directory ./lib/tomcat of the unpacked skeleton
        distribution. There's also a README file in the directory that
        may contain other helpful information.
      </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="http://ant.apache.org/">ant</a> &gt; 1.6.2
      </td>
      <td>
          Apache Ant, the Java-based build tool in version 1.6.2 or higher.
          If you have really large projects consider increasing the memory
          for the java vm ant runs in: Set the ANT_OPTS environment variable 
          to something like "-mx200m". This variable is evaluated within 
          the ant start script contained in the ant distribution.
      </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>
        <a href="http://oss.software.ibm.com/developerworks/opensource/jikes/">jikes</a>
      </td>
      <td>
        <p><b>Optional</b>: <a href="http://www-124.ibm.com/developerworks/oss/jikes/">Jikes</a>
        is a blazingly fast java compiler from IBM. Pustefix is pre-configured to use jikes, so you
        need to install it in order for the build system to work out of the box. <b>Important</b>
        You don't have to install jikes. In this case, please set the ant property build.compiler 
        to <code>modern</code> when calling ant.</p>
      </td>
    </tr>
    </table>

  </subsection>
  </section>
</body>
</document>
