<document>

  <properties>
    <title>What is Pustefix</title>
  </properties>

  <body>

  <section name="What is Pustefix">

  <p>
    Pustefix is a framework that helps you to develop web based
    applications (referred to as <i>projects</i> here). A high level
    view of the system is given on <a href="overview.html">this</a>
    page. The framework consists of two more or less independent
    parts:
  </p>

  <ul>
    <li>A machinery to apply recursive XSLT transformations that
      produces the UI of the web application. You can learn more about
      this <a href="xml.html">here</a>.</li>
    <li>A Java framework that takes input from the UI to change the
      application data and supplies changes of the application data back
      to the UI. This part is explained in much more detail <a href="java.html">here</a></li>
  </ul>

  <p>
    Together, the framework acts similar to the <i>Model-View-Controller</i> pattern.
  </p>

  </section>
  
  <section name="Development news">
  
  <p>Big news: We have replaced the Java applet based editing area
  with one based completely on JavaScript. Now we finally have a solid
  foundation to build upon. The new editing area has not many
  additional features for the time being, but this will change.  For
  now,</p>
  <ul>
    <li>The syntax highlighting should just work.</li>
    <li>You can indent a line or a selected region by pressing TAB.</li>
    <li>For reasonably sized include parts, it's much faster.</li>
  </ul>

  <p>Other stuff we were working on was mostly refactoring the code on
  our way to XSLT 2.0 and trying to move closer to the usual webapp
  layout of J2EE applications. This is much a work in progress, at the
  moment we have cut a branch SAXON_8 where all this work currently lives.
  </p>
  
  <subsection name="Changes">

  <p>You can see changes with increasing details:</p>
  <ul>  
     <li><p>High level: <a href="changes-report.html">Release announcements</a></p></li>
     <li><p>Mid level: <a href="http://cvs.sourceforge.net/cgi-bin/viewcvs.cgi/pustefix/pfixcore/ChangeLog?rev=HEAD&amp;content-type=text/vnd.viewcvs-markup">ChangeLog</a> file</p></li>
     <li><p>Low level: <a href="changelog-report.html">cvs log messages</a></p></li>
  </ul>

  </subsection>
  </section>
</body>
</document>
