<div>
  <h2>Where to get it?</h2>
  <p>
    <pustefix/> is hosted on <a href="http://sourceforge.net/project/showfiles.php?group_id=72089">Sourceforge</a>. All the files
    and also the CVS tree can be downloaded (or checked out) from there.
  </p>

  <p>
    The downloadable files are called
    <b><i>pfixcore</i></b>-&lt;TYPE>-&lt;VERSION>.&lt;SUFFIX>. This naming scheme was
    choosen because a whole <pustefix/> system always contains your own
    application classes and logic which use the core classes and
    utilities supplied by <i>pfixcore</i>. The files to download are shown in the table below.
  </p>
  <p>
    <table class="stdtable">
      <tr>
        <td>
          <i>Filename</i>
        </td>
        <td>
          <i>Content</i>
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          pfixcore-skel-&lt;VERSION>.tar.gz
        </td>
        <td>
          <p>
            This tar file contains a skeleton directory structure with
            all the things you need to start a new pustefix project.
            The pfixcore.jar and pfixcore-data.tar.gz files mentioned
            below are already contained in the file in the version
            indicated by the VERSION string.</p>
          <p><b>If you don't already have a running pustefix project, start by
            downloading this file.</b> For further updates, it's
            sufficiant to download new pfixcore.jar and
            pfixcore-data.tar.gz files to replace the ones you have currently in your project.
          </p>
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          pfixcore-&lt;VERSION>.jar
        </td>
        <td>
          This jar file contains all java classes that the core system
          needs. Download this file (and the corresponding
          pfixcore-data.tar.gz file) if you want to update an already running <pustefix/> project.
        </td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>
          pfixcore-data-&lt;VERSION>.tar.gz
        </td>
        <td>
          This tar file contains all the XML/XSLT files that are needed by the core system. Download this file (and the corresponding
          pfixcore.jar file) if you want to update an already running <pustefix/> project.
        </td>
      </tr>
    </table>
    
  </p>

  <p>
    Please follow the instructions on the Sourceforge <a href="http://sourceforge.net/cvs/?group_id=72089">CVS page</a>
    if you want to download the source repository for <pustefix/>. The name of the repository is <b><i>pfixcore</i></b>.
  </p>

</div>