<div>
  <h1>The <i>Includes</i> page</h1>
  
  <p>The left frame contains all includes of the current project. To edit one
    include, select it and the right frame will display detailed information.</p>
  
  <p>Additionally, a java applet will pop up that lets you change the currently selected include and
    write the changes back to the <pustefix/> editor server.
  </p>
  
  <table>
    <tr valign="top">
      <td>
        <stdimg src="img/editor_includes.png">
          The <i>Includes</i> page of the <pustefix/> editor.
        </stdimg>
      </td>
      <td>
        <table class="stdtable" style="min-width: 200px; margin: 10px; margin-left: 0px; width: 100%">
          <tr>
            <td>
              <b>Box No. 1</b> contains the branch interface and (possibly) the backup select box. The branch interface
              allows to create or delete product specific branches (see the explanation of
              include parts and branches <a href="xml.html">here</a>). The backup select box appears whenever the
              server has stored older versions of the include.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <b>Box No. 2</b> shows all pages which use the current include. To edit
              one of these pages, select it and it will be opened in the <a href="editor_pages.html">Pages</a> page.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <b>Box No. 3</b> lists all includes which are used by the current include. After clicking
              on such an include it will be selected as the current include.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <b>Box No. 4</b> displays all images which are use by the current include. To edit
              an image select it and it will be opened in the <a href="editor_images.html">Images</a> page.
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              <b>Box No. 5</b> shows the whole content of the current target.
            </td>
          </tr>
        </table>
      </td>
    </tr>
    <tr valign="top">
      <td>
        <stdimg src="img/editor_applet_includes.png">
          The <i>EditorApplet</i> of the <pustefix/> editor
        </stdimg>
      </td>
      <td>
        <table class="stdtable" style="min-width: 200px; margin: 10px; margin-left: 0px; width: 100%">
          <tr>
            <td>
              This is the <i>EditorApplet</i>. It opens whenever you select an include
              in the left frame and lets you edit and upload this include. 
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              Pressing the <i>Submit</i>-button will upload all changes you made in the
              <i>EditorApplet</i>. After upload your changes will be visible in the
              affected page(s).
            </td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>
              Pressing the <i>Close</i>-button will close the <i>EditorApplet</i> and
              discard all changes.
            </td>
          </tr>
        </table>
      </td>
    </tr>
  </table>
</div>
