<div>
  <h1>Project definition</h1>
  <p>For each project in your <pustefix/> environment you need to create a definition file that contains all the
    information about your project that is needed to automatically generate other configuration files for various sbsystems.</p>
  <ul>
    <li>The <b>apache</b> config file, containing the definition for each of the projects of your environment:<br/>
      <code>servletconf/tomcat/apache.conf</code></li>
    <li>The config files for <b>mod_jk</b>:<br/>
      <code>servletconf/tomcat/jk.conf</code> and <code>servletconf/tomcat/workers.prop</code>.
    </li>
    <li>The config file for the <b>tomcat</b> servlet container:<br/>
      <code>servletconf/tomcat/conf/server.xml</code></li>
    <li>The config files for every <b>webapp</b> (each project is mapped to a webapp):<br/>
      <code>servletconf/tomcat/webapps/[project name]/WEB-INF/web.xml</code>
    </li>
    <li>The config file that tells the <a href="editor.html"><pustefix/> editor</a> about all the projects that
      can be edited in your environment:<br/>
      <code>common/conf/products.prj</code></li>
  </ul>

  <p>This information is contained in a site wide file
    <code>servletconf/projects.xml.in</code> which contains information
    every environment needs. Each project also needs to supply a file to tell the
    system it's own configuration. These files are at <code>[project
      name]/conf/project.xml.in</code>. All those files, together with the
    site wide file are used as the source for creating the above
    mentioned config files.
  </p>

  <h2>The site wide configuration <i>servletconf/projects.xml.in</i></h2>

  <p>The site wide projects.xml.in file contains two "projects" that are
    needed for <pustefix/> itself to work properly.  The first of these
    is the <a href="editor.html">editor</a> project. The other project
    is used to start a servlet automatically when the system
    starts. This servlet itself is not able to act on any userinput,
    it's only purpose is to start a bunch of factories that implement
    functionality shared by other, "real" projects.</p>
  
  <p>If you need other servlets for administrative purposes (e.g. to
    gather some sort of statisitics about the system as a whole) you can
    add these servlets to this project.</p>
  
  <h2>The project specific configuration <i>[project name]/conf/project.xml.in</i></h2>

  <p>
    
  </p>
  
  </div>